10 days ago, Jeff Nippert released his
latest video on YouTube titled The Best
and Worst Glute Exercises Ranked Using
Science. So, Jeff has 6.7 million
followers. Um, he's done a great job of
pushing science onto Everyday Bros., and
I commend him for that. He ranked a ton
of popular glute exercises from S for
super and then A, B, C, D, and E, and
then F for fail. And he separated them
by region. And I want to react to this
video because it's right down my alley.
You know, I have a ton of respect for
Jeff. What I like about this is that if
there's a disagreement, he's the type of
guy who will help me fund a study. He's
funded research before. So has Mike
Isertel. So has Jeremy Ethier. So has
Menow Hanselman. So between the four of
us, we're expanding our knowledge and
investigating popular topics. So no
shade intended on Jeff. Like I said, I
have tremendous respect for him. He
probably expects this coming and I've
already watched the video. I agree with
90% of it. But one thing I want you to
pay attention to is Jeff is a lifter.
You know, he doesn't train a ton of
people like I do. Most of the popular
experts on YouTube and in social media
in general, they don't have a gym. They
don't train, you know, 30 people, 60
people like I do. Because I train so
many people, I'm going to have a unique
viewpoint on some of the stuff compared
to Jeff. Whereas Jeff is going to have a
unique viewpoint compared to me. And I'm
sure if Jeff were here every day in
Glute Lab witnessing what I did, he'd
probably agree with me on some of my
reaction. Enough of that. Let's dive
into it. So, I'm just going to hit play
and I'll pause when necessary.
The glutes are one of the single most
important muscles for building an
impressive physique. They're also one of
the largest muscles in the body. So,
regardless of whether you're a man or
you're a woman, building this one muscle
will make it immediately obvious that
you lift from the side and the rear. So,
in this video, I'm ranking the best and
worst glute exercises for muscle growth
using the latest exercise science. We'll
go from S tier for super all the way
down to F tier for fail. And at the end,
I'll show you what I think are the very
best and the very worst glute exercises
of all time. Now, in order to figure out
which exercises are better, we need to
understand some very basic glute anatomy
first. The glutials are technically
three distinct muscles. There's the very
large glutius maximus, which is the real
powerhouse of your lower body. It
extends your hips like in a deadlift and
externally rotates your leg, like when
you point your toes out. There's the
glutius medius, which is about 1/3 of
the size of the glutius maximus, but
it's still well worth focusing on. It's
still quite big. It has about the same
amount of muscle mass as your delts, and
since it sits on the upper glutes, it'll
enhance that appearance of a upper glute
shelf. The glute medius is very active
during hip abduction. Okay, I'm going to
pause this. I don't think the glute
medius is that active in seated hip
abduction when you're leaning forward.
maybe the posterior fibers, but um I
think the upper glute max and if you
lean even more forward, even the lower
glute max gets involved here. So I think
this right here, what he's showing, the
glute medius fibers are more vertical.
They would not help out as much in that
particular variation compared to glutus
maximus and then the deep six hip
external rotators where you sweep your
leg out to the side and it's a very
important stabilizer. So, it's
especially active during single leg
exercises. And there's the even smaller
glute minimus, which is about half the
size of the glute medius, but also plays
a key stabilization role and can add
size to the upper glutes. In addition to
being split into those three separate
muscles, your glutes can also be divided
into an upper, middle, and lower
portion. And as we go, I'll reveal my
number one exercise for each division of
the glutes hidden behind these three
doors. So, keep in mind that just
because an exercise gets into S tier
doesn't necessarily mean it's S tier for
the entire glutes. It might be S tier
for targeting one specific area. And
here's my criteria for ranking glute
exercises. To get into S tier, the
exercise needs to provide high tension,
especially in the stretched position.
Okay, I'm going to pause it right there.
For the glutes, the jury is still out as
to whether it's best to train them in a
lengthened or shortened position. We
only have a few studies, but the main
study is the Plotkin 2023 study, which
compared squats to hip thrust. Now, if
you think about it, squats involve more
length and more torque at long length.
So, it's not just that they stretch your
glutes more, they also provide more
torque in the stretch position. So, if
this were a rule, like longer is always
better, then squats would have
necessarily beat out hip thrust. But the
fact that they tied for upper, middle,
and lower glutes shows that maybe
there's more to the story because hipos
are hardest in the shortened position
and they have a lot more torque in the
shortened position. So for that reason
alone, I don't agree with number one
being a criteria across the board for
all muscles. I just gave a seminar.
There are 47 articles pertaining to this
topic. It's fascinating. In fact, 15
articles have emerged just in the past
year. This is the most rapid growing
body of research. But I'm not convinced
for glutes yet. But let's go on. It
should feel good, which means it doesn't
cause knee, hip, or low back pain. And
there should be some way of progressing
the exercise over time, which is
ultimately what'll keep your glutes
growing. Okay, let's start with the most
popular glute exercise on the internet,
the hip thrust. The barbell hip thrust
is, oddly enough, one of the more
studied movements in all of exercise
science. There's a pile of studies
showing that it is in fact very
effective at growing the glutes. The hip
thrust will activate the entire glute,
upper, middle, and lower, but mainly
target that middle meat because it
isolates hip extension. It's a great
movement for progressive overload. You
can almost always add a little weight
each week while keeping your form tight.
I don't think you need a 500 lb hip
thrust to grow your glutes, but if your
glutes are getting stronger on this
movement, somewhere in the 5 to 15 rep
range, then your glutes are also getting
bigger. There is a slight issue, though.
A lot of people find that the barbell
pinches their hips. You can alleviate
this to some degree by using a big cushy
pad or even rolling up some yoga mats or
by strategically placing the bar in that
cushy crease of your hip below the
anterior superior iliac spine and above
the pubic bone. But even if you avoid
that painful pinching, it can still feel
awkward. It also takes time to set up,
especially if you don't have a hip
thruster platform or if you're loading a
lot of plates. The hip thrust also
doesn't get the glutes into a super deep
stretch. Even a deep range of motion hip
thrust only gets the glutes into about
90° of hip flexion compared to the 130
degrees of range that's possible for
most lifters. But this isn't as much of
a dealbreaker as you might think. I
don't know that the glutes need an ultra
deep stretch to grow. A recent 9-week
study with untrained subjects found that
the hip thrust was just as effective as
the squat at growing the glutes despite
the fact that the squat does stretch the
glutes more. Now, that's just one study
and other research does suggest that the
glutes respond well to deeper training.
I'm going to pause it right there. That
graph came from the Kubo study, which
showed that deeper squats grew the
glutes and the adductors better than
partial squats, but not the quads. Quad
growth tied between the two. But they
only disclosed the knee range of motion
in that study, and they didn't have
pictures. I'm really glad that modern
researchers like Daniel Plin, Milo Wolf,
and PAC, these guys are uploading
pictures and videos of all the exercise
subjects. So there's no doubt as to the
form and technique that was used during
the studies. With the Kubo study, I'm
sure if you did low bar and sat way
back, that would require tremendous
torque at the hips and it would probably
build the glutes well. But that study
involved beginners, they probably did
high bar, stayed super upright, and just
did a little knee bend. That's why they
got such good quad growth out of it. So,
I would love to replicate the Kubo
study, but have subjects sit back
because a partial squat can actually be
effective for glute building if you sit
way back and utilize the hips. But I
digress. Let's move on. So, like other
muscles, I suspect the glutes will grow
best from a combination of exercises
that challenge them in a more stretched
position like the squat, plus exercises
that challenge them in a more shortened
position like the hip thrust. All right,
I'm going to pause there. Totally agree
with that. and to add to create the best
programming that maximizes the
recoverable volume so you can do a ton
of volume of both stretched and
shortened glute work. So, I'm really
glad Jeff mentioned that. As an overall
glute max builder, I'm putting the
barbell hip thrust into high B tier.
Now, if you have access to a good hip
thrust machine like this Nautilus glute
drive, I think you can solve a few of
those issues. The belt is much more
comfy than a barbell. You also don't
need to set anything up. And because the
machine is very stable, you won't need
to use any balance and should be able to
focus on engaging your glutes better. I
personally do these every single week
and I think they belong in high A tier
and I'm actually going to pick them as
my number one option for the middle
aspect of the glutes. Their only
downside, as I see it, is the lack of a
really deep stretch, but we'll pick that
up with some other exercises. Another
really, this is where my expertise comes
into play cuz bros love the Nautilus
glute drive. I love it. Um, but I had it
in Glue San Diego for a couple years and
only one of my female clients liked it
out of like 30. 29 of them felt it all
in their quads and only one of them
loved it. What's ironic is that she was
a shorter client. I love the Nautilus
glute drive. Jeff loves it, but most
women do not. As you can see in that
video, it did allow you to go deeper and
it is very stable. I wish Jeff could try
the BC strength thruster pro. I think
that's better than the Nautilus glute
drive. I think it's the best plate
loaded hip thrust machine on the market.
Second being hammer strength. But I'm
gonna go off on a little tangent here.
Whenever I'm working really hard on back
squats, I find that my hack squat, my
leg press, my belt squats, my pendulum
squats, my V squats, they all stay
strong. Squats are the one exercise that
keeps all of those strong. But the
converse isn't true. If you're doing
hack squats, your back squat will go
down. And it's the same thing in my
experience for hip thrust. You can do
all the plate loaded devices, the
selectorized devices, all the glute
drives, and it'll make your barbell hip
thrust go down. But conversely, when
you're doing barbell hip thrusts, your
strength on all the machines stays high.
Why? Because they're so hard in the
lockout. When you haven't done barbell
in a while and you do them, you're like,
"Oh my god, the lockout is hard." So, I
do wonder if machines are superior to
barbell. With regards to the hip thrust,
there should be a study on this in time.
But I like hearing Jeff's opinion on
that because it is more stable. It's
more convenient. It doesn't require any
setup. And the more convenient something
is, the more often you'll do it in the
gym. Good option is the single leg
dumbbell hip thrust. These will hit the
entire glutes, but unlike the other
options, may shift some emphasis to the
upper glutes because the glute medius
and minimus will need to stabilize for
balance. You can also prevent left. This
applies to all single leg movements.
People always say, well, it's going to
work the glute medius and minimus well
for the stabilization factor. I'm not
sold that the glute medius gets hit hard
with single leg movements. You're not
moving dynamically side to side. You're
just stabilizing. So, you're never going
to fire maximally in a stabilizing role.
I'm not aware of any research that shows
market glute medius growth from
anything, but my guess is that any
single leg movement, including single
leg hip thrust, including all the lunges
and split squats and step-ups, the
single leg RDL, I'm not sure if they'd
grow the glute medius that much. What I
think is that they're harder as you bend
down. And the more you bend down, the
more glute maximus it's going to work.
All right, let's continue. Prevent left
to right muscle imbalances by focusing
on each glute individually. And I don't
like to go heavy here. Just stick to 12
to 15 reps and really focus on
controlling the movement. They're going
in A tier as well. The glute bridge is
really just a hip thrust but with less
range of motion. They're a bit easier to
set up because you don't need a bench
and they're great for beginners because
they require less stabilization. Some
people also say they can isolate their
glutes more with these by taking some of
the quads out, but I still prefer the
hip thrust because it has more range of
motion. Low B tier. Frog pumps. I
totally agree with him there. I like
glute bridges off the Smith machine
because you can use a more fuller rom.
But if your main interest is growing
your glutes without growing the legs,
then I think glute bridges are your main
exercise. Pumps are also kind of like a
hip thrust except you externally rotate
your hips and clamp your feet together.
This will shift some emphasis to the
upper glutes since abducting your hips
will engage the glute medius more.
Actually, I don't think that it works
that way. I think frog pumps
interestingly activate the upper and
lower glutes really well. But that
external rotation and abduction, I think
it just lines up. You know, the glutes
are a diagonal muscle. I think when you
abduct and externally rotate, it just
lines up the fibers a little bit better
and improves their moment arm. But
getting in that stance or even doing
like a sumo deadlift, yes, you're
abducted, but but the glute medius isn't
providing that abduction. You just set
up that way. So, I don't think frog
pumps are going to activate the glute
medius or minimus. I think it works by
just putting the glute maximus in better
alignment. I don't hate these as a high
rep finisher, but they're hard to load,
which forces you to use really high
reps, and they don't stretch the glutes
very well. We do frog pumps off the
Smith machine as well, which allows you
to go heavy. I will add that I feel my
glutes more on frog pumps than any other
exercise, but my feet tend to be turned
out. So, if you're like me, frog pumps
could be an S or an A tier exercise,
whereas for other people like to have
narrow stance with everything. I even
have a client who likes to turn her feet
inwards a little bit. They would be an F
tier exercise for her. I'm putting them
in high Ctier. All right, so let's take
a look at some exercises that actually
do stretch the glutes quite a lot. We'll
start with squats. I think squats are a
super underrated glute builder on social
media. Like the hip thrust, you're
extending your hips, so you'll activate
all regions of the glutes, but
especially that middle chunk. I would
say most of my own glute development
does come from squats and my background
in powerlifting. The only potential
downside of squats is that they don't
really isolate the glutes well. You get
a huge quad stimulus, too. So, if you're
only trying to grow your glutes without
growing your quads, squats aren't your
best option. that I would also say a
huge adductor stimulus especially if you
go really deep. Said you can make the
movement more glute dominant by placing
the bar a few inches lower on your back,
leaning further forward, and focusing on
really driving through your hips. Also,
research shows that squatting deeper is
important for glute growth. So, try to
at least break parallel. Despite some
limitations, I'm still putting the
barbell squat in a tier for glute
growth. With the Smith machine squat,
you can place your feet further forward
to make it more glute dominant, and you
never need to worry about losing your
balance. It's also going in a tier. The
Bulgarian split squat gets a deeper
stretch on the glutes than the standard
barbell squat. And because they're
single leg, in addition to the middle
glutes, you'll get the upper glutes more
involved. To make them even more glute
focused, place your front foot further
forward and lean forward as you squat.
Again, think about driving through your
hips rather than just standing up with
your knees. This will help you engage
your glutes a lot better. These are very
close to S tier, but they are a bit
harder to overload, especially if you do
them with dumbbells. They also smoke
your quads and are a really exhausting
movement in general. I usually do two
sets per leg and call it there. I'm
feeling I love that Jeff pointed that
out. He does two sets per leg. Sometimes
if I do a single leg movement, I I might
even do one set per leg because they
beat me up so much. Once you get really
really strong, they beat you up a lot
and they interfere with your training
frequency. You don't need to worry about
that if you train legs once a week. But
if you're training glutes three times a
week like most of the females out there,
then you have to take that into
consideration. High eight here. Before I
get to our first S tier exercise, let's
knock out a couple duds. Donkey kicks
probably don't grow your glutes very
well. They're really hard to overload.
Even with a band, you're still getting
very little tension while the glutes are
stretched. And it's hard to
progressively overload using a band
anyway. I think they're solid as a
warm-up activation drill or to help
beginners feel their glutes engage, but
as a glute hypertrophy exercise, these
are going in low D tier. Fire hydrants
have similar issues. They just don't get
high tension on the glutes. They can
work for mobility or in rehab context,
but I'm putting them in low D tier as a
glute builder. All right, let's look at
some exercises that target the upper
glutes. Hickbacks are great for the
upper glutes, especially if you kick up
and out diagonally. That's because the
upper glute fibers perform both hip
extension, which is the up part, and hip
abduction, which is the out and
diagonally part. Kickbacks are actually
very stable if you brace against the
machine, and perhaps even more stable if
you brace against a bench. The
resistance profile should feel nice and
smooth. You don't get the biggest
stretch, but that can be made up with
other exercises that we'll get to. I
don't do a whole lot of kickbacks
myself, but I do think they're a really
great option if you like them or if you
want to isolate the glutes without
hitting quads. Yeah, I've never really
seen any bros that do kickbacks. I
started doing them. It took me a while
cuz the hip flexor on my my stabilizing
leg took a beating. I had to strengthen
that for kickbacks to feel good. But I
will mention Glute Builder came out with
a kickback machine. It is amazing. Um
it's so good. Also, I want to mention
that you can do kneeling kickbacks or
high pulley kickbacks to make it kind of
more like a step up to put more torque
in the stretch position and less torque
at the lockout. You can shift the torque
angle or the strength curve around to
suit your preference. But my main
kickback I like is the swoopy standing
upright kickback. And I really like it
because it's like penalty-free volume.
You really don't get sore from it. So,
my girls will always throw kickbacks in
at the end of the workout. I'm thinking
low A tier. Step-ups will target the
upper glutes because you're doing one
leg at a time and the stability
requirement engages the glute medius and
minimus. They get a deep stretch on the
entire glute, especially if you set the
box a little higher at or just above
knee level, which will force your glutes
to work harder than your quads. If you
have a handle to grab onto, you can keep
your balance better and overload the
glutes even more. They can be a bit
awkward at first, but once you learn how
to engage your glutes more than your
quads, I think they're killer. Low A
tier machine hip. I totally agree about
step-ups. Interestingly, step-ups don't
tend to get people as sore as lunges and
Bulgarian split squats. So, they can be
performed more frequently. That's one
thing in the last two years here at
Glute Lab Fort Lauderdale, we've done
way more of is glute dominant step-ups,
and I think it's been beneficial. But
again, I don't think it works the glute
medius and minimus that well. We need
research on that because I could very
well be wrong. The glute medius is going
to fire hardest when you're upright. The
exercise isn't that challenging up tall.
It's challenging at the bottom where the
glute medius doesn't have good leverage.
The glute max does. And if you got to
the top and fired your glute medius as
hard as you can, you'd move to the side.
So, anytime a muscle is just a
stabilizer, it just fires it the right
amount to maintain balance, but not
maximally. Machine hip abductions are
fantastic for the upper glutes. That's
because they really challenge the glute
medius and minimus directly through
their primary function of hip abduction.
Seated hip abduction leaning forward I
think will work the posterior fibers of
the glute medius and minimus but not the
anterior middle in my opinion and
they'll involve the upper glute max and
possibly the lower glute max will and
then the deep six hip external rotators
but this is an area I'd love to see
research on too because if you look at
the fiber directions of the glute medius
they're not well aligned for leaning
seated hip abduction however you can
just bridge up and do a hip thrust and
then do bridged seated hip abduction and
then you're really targeting the glute
medius for that reason at my glute labs
we always do two typ types of seated hip
abduction. One leaning forward and one
bridged. Leaning forward for the glute
max, bridged for the glute mection. If
you lean forward by about 30°, you'll
improve the line of pull of those upper
glute fibers and you should feel a
deeper stretch at the bottom. I usually
do these for 15 to 20 reps, although
heavier low rep work is also good. You
can always progressively overload the
movement by just increasing the pin
weight. And when you eventually max out
the stack, you can use a gym pin to add
more if you want a little. We always do
around 20 rep sets. This is one exercise
that when you go super super heavy, it
doesn't feel as good. So, don't feel the
need to do sets of six or anything. That
tends to irritate your hips and activate
more TFL. So, always high reps on those
in my opinion. Extra range of motion.
You can add an extra pad on the inside.
And while it may not be the best overall
glute builder, it's just so good at
targeting the upper glutes. And for that
reason, it's our first exercise going
into S tier. And it's also my number one
exercise for the upper glutes, making it
the reveal behind door number one. Cable
hip abductions do the So, that being his
number one exercise for upper glutes.
Maybe it is for upper glute max. I don't
think it is for glute me and men, but we
need research on that cuz that's
something we should all know. Hip
abductions do the same basic thing, but
I find them harder to overload. They're
not quite as stable and they're a bit
more annoying to set up. I'm thinking B
tier. The lateral banded walk is the I
wish Jeff could try the glute medius hip
thrust. I wonder if he'd like that.
That's my favorite upper glute exercise.
But I do think in order to maximize
glute meat and mid growth, you should do
po possibly like seated hip abduction
for the posterior and then like straight
out to the side for more like anterior
and middle and then angled back 30° for
more of the bulk of the glute medius
like the middle fibers. But there are
some movements he might like including
the glute medius hip thrust. Same basic
movement pattern, but the band offers
virtually zero tension in the stretch.
These are fine enough as a warm-up drill
or for helping people engage their glute
medius better, but they're just not
going to add much meat to your glutes
unless you're a beginner. I'm putting
them one exception I will tell you, I
had given all my girls glute loops and
during the quarantine they were so bored
they had nothing to do. So every single
day they were doing kickbacks and
standing hip abduction with the glute
loop and their glutes grew like crazy
during the quarantine. So that's what's
tricky about this. If you're willing to
train glutes every day, band standing
hip abduction is brilliant. I don't like
lateral band walks as much, but I do
like bandstanding hip abduction, but
yes, they work at short muscle lengths,
but they deliver a serious pump. I will
tell you, most guys go to do them and
they're so insanely weak at them. Like,
my girls are way stronger in hip
abduction than most men are. So, the
devil's in the details. These don't
create any muscle damage, so you can do
them frequently. No guy that I've ever
known cares so much about glute medius
growth that they will be willing to do,
you know, glute loop workouts every
night, but the ladies are. Another
observation, men tend to get these
bubbly glutes. We don't really need to
do abduction. We don't need to train the
glute medius to have the shelf, but a
lot of women do. But I do agree if you
just train legs or glutes one day a
week, it would be far more effective to
use a cable column than a band if just
doing them one day a week. But if you're
doing them every day, the band would be
superior in my opinion. Them in C tier.
Okay, speaking of stretching the glutes,
let's talk about lunges. Lunges will hit
the entire glute. You'll get the upper
glutes because of glute medius
activation due to the stabilization
demands. You'll get the mid glutes from
the hip extension and the lower glute
area from the deep stretch as you lunge.
You can accentuate that stretch by
taking longer strides forward and by
leaning slightly forward by about 30°.
There are many different ways to do
lunges, but I like old school walking
lunges the best. I like the idea that
you're moving through space. It gives
you something to actually work toward
rather than just doing reps on the spot.
I find that more motivating. And sure,
while you can probably get a slightly
better stretch with Bulgarian split
squats, if you take big steps on lunges,
you'll feel a massive glute stretch,
too. And even though soreness isn't
everything, I get more sore from lunges
than anything else. I do, too. I get
more sore from lunges than anything.
They also make my adductor magnus sore.
And this is a strange thing to say, but
they're almost too effective. They
annihilate me so bad. They make me too
sore. Theoretically, the repeated bout
effect, you should stop getting sore.
But for me, they hit me so hard in the
adductor magnus and the lower glutes.
They get my glutes so tight. A lot of
times I hurt my back in the days
following walking lunges because my
glutes are so tight. I end up moving
differently and hurting my back picking
something up off the floor. I've also
had times where like two days after
doing a heavy walking lunge workout, I
remember my stepbrother jumped on my
back and I pulled my adductors. Like I
strained my adductors. They were so
damaged. My female clients can lunge up
and down. They don't get too sore. But
for me, lunges get my glutes more sore
than anything. And it's strange because
I think that's evidence that they're so
effective at targeting the glutes in the
stretch position. They require so much
torque. But then I can injure myself.
And if I did like four sets, I would be
sore for like eight days. I don't think
I could walk the next day if I did four
sets, like close to failure. So, I'm
glad he said that because yes, people
say soreness is overrated, but if an
exercise gets you really sore, it's
usually an indicator that's a very
effective exercise. But if you train
glutes three times a week, you probably
can't get away with doing walking lunges
every single workout. For my female
clients, if they train glutes Monday,
Wednesday, Friday, I program them on the
Fridays so that they get an extra day of
recovery before they hit them again on
Monday. I'm a huge fan of walking lunges
and I'm sending them straight to S tier.
Smith machine lunges have all the same
benefits, but again, I just don't like
doing all my reps on the spot when I
have the option to move through space.
That's more of a personal preference
thing, but I'm still putting these in
high A tier. If you elevate your front
foot on a small box, you'll get a bit
more range of motion at the bottom,
which is just enough to sneak these into
S tier with curtsy. Well, all right. If
you compare his video of the Smith
machine reverse lunge and the deficit
reverse lunge, I think you're getting a
similar stretch. You're getting more
torque with a standard variation.
Sometimes when you elevate the front
foot for deficit, you go deeper, but
torque diminishes because your hips move
under the bar and it shortens the moment
arm and it ends up getting you a similar
stretch. It's not just the stretch, it's
the tension in the stretch that matters
more. So, for that reason, I think that
regular reverse lunges are better than
deficit lunges. You step back diagonally
behind your other leg. This requires
more balance, meaning it'll activate the
glute medius more. So, another good
option for the upper glutes. That said,
I think because they're harder to
overload, I don't think they're quite as
good as a standard lunge. They're
definitely an option you can include
every now and then, but I'm feeling low
B tier. Okay, let's cover three lower
glute. I agree about the curtsy lunge.
Um, I wish Jeff could try this new
exercise we've been doing, the kneeling
dumbbell hip raise. It's like a curtsy
lunge done in a kneeling position that
gets high stretch and high torque in the
stretch position, but it takes the quads
and possibly the adductors out of it.
There's this kind of nifty little
exercise that behaves similar to the
curtsy lunge that has all the good stuff
about the curtsy lunge without all the
bad stuff, especially with the B stance
option builders. First up, the deadlift.
The conventional deadlift is a good
glute builder since it trains hip
extension. It gives a big stretch on the
lower glutes and it's amazing for
progressive overload. The issue is it's
just such a fatiguing exercise
physically and psychologically. This is
why it's said to have a low stimulus to
fatigue ratio. You get a lot of
stimulus, but you also get a lot of
fatigue, especially in muscles other
than the glutes, like the spinal
erectors. As a strength builder, it's
elite, but as a glute hypertrophy
exercise, I have to put it in low B
tier. The sumo deadlift is very similar.
This EMG study found no difference in
glute maximus EMG activity between
conventional and sumo stances. That
said, because of the hip abduction and
hip external rotation from the wider
stance and the foot flare, the sumo
deadlift probably does hit the glute
medius harder and might Yeah, I don't
think it hits the glute medius harder. I
just think it improves the moment arm of
the glute max. But I will say that
Escamilla study didn't show a
difference, but there's probably like 12
EMG studies looking at sumo versus
conventional. Almost every study shows
an advantage for sumo with EMG. So sumo
probably activates the glutes better
whereas conventional stretches the
glutes better with a narrow stance. So
which is more important stretch or
activation? Well, think of the plotin
study. Hip thrusts activate the glutes
more. Squats stretch the glutes more and
they tied for muscle growth. And they
probably grow muscle through independent
mechanisms. One pertaining to activation
and active force production, the other
pertaining to stretch and passive muscle
force. So you probably need both types
of exercises for maximum glute growth.
and might shift some emphasis toward the
upper glutes. I'm putting it in high B
tier as a glute builder. The Romanian
deadlift is the better choice for glute
hypertrophy in my opinion, especially
for the lower glutes in that glute
hamstring tie-in area. And while it does
hit the hamstrings hard as well, it
smashes the glute max as a basic
compound lift that's very conducive to
progressive overload. I'm feeling high A
tier. And this is actually my number one
exercise for the lower glutes, but it's
not my number one exercise of all.
Before we get to that, let's knock out
three final exercises. One that I love,
one that I hate, and one that's just
okay. I love the 45°ree back extension.
A lot of people think of it as just a
low back exercise, but since you're
extending your hips, your entire glutes
will be very active in both the lengthen
position at the bottom and the shorten
position at the top. I prefer to
overload these by adding reps, but you
can still work up to some solid weight
by holding plates to your chest. If you
round your upper back on these, you
should be able to connect with your
glutes much better. I'm honestly feeling
S tier for these. I would also say flare
your feet out a little more as that
leads to better lockouts and slightly
greater glute activation. But I'm glad
Jeff mentioned the rounding of the upper
back because when you round your upper
back, you're taking the erectors out of
it. But what you're also doing is
increasing the torque at the lockout. If
you're arched, it's less torque compared
if you're rounded because you stick out
further from the hip joint center. So
more torque at lockout is a good thing
if you're using this for the squeeze
position. So, like an RDL for the
stretch position and a 45 hyper for the
squeeze position. They complement each
other well. Cable pullthroughs are okay
for me. They're great for beginners
without much glute strength, but
eventually you'll be limited by how much
weight you can hold comfortably. They
just start to feel awkward once you get
some real weight on there. I'm thinking
low B tier. I'm unless you're pregnant.
If you're pregnant, the pullthrough
becomes an A tier exercise. But I agree
with Jeff here. Not a big fan of kettle
bell swings. You can definitely get a
good cardio workout with these, and I
think they do have some utility for
building explosive power, but for glute
hypertrophy, you're just not getting
enough tension. Low Dtier. Okay. And if
I had to pick just one exercise from S
tier to raise it up to S tier plus as
the best of the best, I think I'd have
to go with the walking lunge. I realize
that's a hot take, but these are all
great glute builders, and if I had to
personally just pick one, I think it
would be the walking lunge. And I'll go
with the donkey kick or the fire hydrant
as the worst of the worst. Not because
they can't have their place as warm-up
drills, but it's just really hard to
reach high glute tension for muscle
growth. I'm actually really trying to
bring up my own glutes this year, so I'm
doing a ton of hip thrusts, hip
abductions, and walking lunges. But it's
not enough to just dial your training
in. Your diet is also crucial. You need
to ensure that you're eating the right
number of calories and protein to
support muscle growth. And so many
people still underestimate the impact of
diet on your physique. Dialing in my own
diet over the last year made a gigantic
difference in my progress. So, if you'd
like to get on track yourself, you can
download my nutrition app, MacroFactor,
for two weeks for free if you use code
Jeff. And I'll put a link to that over
here next to my head. All right, that's
it for this one, guys. Thank you so much
for watching. Don't forget to leave me a
thumbs up if you enjoyed the video.
Subscribe if you haven't already, and
I'll see you all here in the next one.
Man, 1.1 million views in 10 days. I
wish I never gave up on YouTube. Uh, I
had a few hundred,000 followers many
years ago, and I switched all my focus
to Instagram, but long format has always
been my thing. I'm not good at the short
form content, but this is a great video.
Jeff did an awesome job. He knocked it
out of the park with this. Honestly, my
list wouldn't be that much different
from his because ultimately I think it's
the combination of exercises that matter
most. I do think the walking lunge is
probably the best exercise for the lower
glute. But that's an interesting topic
too because the Plotkins study showed
that squats and hip thrust built the
same amount of upper, middle, and lower
glute max and neither grew the glute
medius. So, the jury is still out as to
whether you can target upper and lower
glute. You definitely feel more soreness
in the lower glutes from walking lunges.
You definitely get higher glute EMG
activity in the upper glute max from
like hip thrusts and back extensions and
kickbacks, but you can target different
subdivisions of the glute max cuz right
now that's lacking. But like I said, I
would agree that the walking lunge is
the best lower glute exercise, but it's
just too good. And Jeff's a bro. He
probably trains lower body twice a week.
And I think he probably doesn't relate
well to women who train glutes three
times a week. For that reason, I might
choose the step up over the walking
lunge. Not because I think it's better,
but because it doesn't fatigue you as
much and you can perform it more
frequently. I think I like the barbell
hip thrust over the nois glute drive
because I want the hardest glute
exercise at the lockout and that's
definitely the barbell hip thrust. I do
agree with him that if you had to just
do one, the novice glute drive takes you
through more range of motion and it's
more stable. But again, it's the
combination of exercises. So, because we
have an exercise already that's so
effective for the lengthen position, the
walking lunge or the step up, then I
would pick the barbell hip thrust. And
lately, we've been hip thrusting on the
glute builder ramp, which I like the
most. My female clients, they all like
the rotisserie hip thrust the best off
the rotating pad, which is interesting
because that almost takes away some of
the hip thrust properties. When you
rotate, it's harder at the bottom and
it's easy at the lockout, which is
opposite of the standard barbell hip
thrust. And then for upper glutes, I'd
go with the glute medius hip thrust with
a close second being the glute medius
kickback, but probably done the way
coach Cass recommends, which is to
really stretch the glute and have high
torque in that stretch position. And
it's really stable. The way he does it,
I think is the most effective. But I
could see the logic in everything Jeff
said. Again, Jeff knocked this out of
the park. Much respect to him. If you're
very popular and you make a video on
glutes, I'm probably going to react to
it because this is my jam. Again, what I
love about Jeff is if we ever disagreed
on something, Jeff, Jeremy Ethier, Mike
Isertel, Menow Hensmans, we would
actually say, "Hey, let's fund a study.
Let's see who's right." And I love that
for the first time in strength and
conditioning history, you've got popular
social media influencers funding
research. So, two thumbs up for Jeff.
Much respect. Anyways, I hope you like
the video. Be sure to like it and make
sure you subscribe to my channel if
glutes are your jam, just like mine. I'm
Brez, aka the glute guy.